I want you to imagine
أريد منكم أن تتخيلوا
what a breakthrough this was
هذا التقدم الذي طرأ
for women who were victims of violence
للنساء المتعنفات
in the 1980s.
في الثمانينيات .
They would come into the emergency room
حيث كن يأتين الى غرفة الطوارئ
with what the police would call "a lovers' quarrel,"
وبهم اثار ما تسميه الشرطة &amp;quot; شجار العاشق &amp;quot;
and I would see a woman who was beaten,
حينها كنت ارى امرأة قد تعرضت للضرب
I would see a broken nose and a fractured wrist
و كنت ارى انف مكسور و رسغ محطم
and swollen eyes.
و عينان متورمتان .
And as activists, we would take our Polaroid camera,
و كنشطاء حقوقين كنا نأخذ كاميراتنا من نوع بولارويد,
we would take her picture,
و نلتقط صورتها ,
we would wait 90 seconds,
و بعدها ننتظر لمدة تسعون ثانية ,
and we would give her the photograph.
ثم نعطيها الصورة
And she would then have
حينها سوف تمتلك
the evidence she needed to go to court.
الدليل التي تحتاجه للذهاب الى المحكمة .
We were making what was invisible visible.
كنا نجعل من الخفي مرئيا .
I've been doing this for 30 years.
لازلت اقوم بهذا العمل لمدة ثلاثون سنة
I've been part of a social movement
كنت جزأ من حركة اجتماعية .
that has been working on ending
و التي كانت تعمل من اجل انهاء
violence against women and children.
العنف ضد النساء و الاطفال
And for all those years,
و طوال هذا السنين كلها
I've had an absolutely passionate
كان لدي ايمان شغوف
and sometimes not popular belief
و في بعض الاحيان غير شائع
that this violence is not inevitable,
بأن هذا العنف ليس بالامر المحتوم
that it is learned, and if it's learned,
بل أنه مكتسب , و اذا كان بالفعل مكتسبا
it can be un-learned, and it can be prevented.
يمكن منعه و التخلص منه .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Why do I believe this?
لماذا اؤمن بهذا ؟
Because it's true.
لانه شي صحيح .
It is absolutely true.
انه صحيح مطلقا .
Between 1993 and 2010,
بين عام 1993 و عام 2010
domestic violence among adult women
العنف المنزلي بين النساء الراشدات
in the United States
في الولايات المتحدة
has gone down by 64 percent,
انخقض بنسبة 64 في المئة ,
and that is great news.
وهذه اخبار عظيمة .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Sixty-four percent. Now, how did we get there?
اربعة و ستون بالمئة . الان كيف وصلنا الى هذا ؟
Our eyes were wide open.
اعيننا كانت مفتوحة .
Thirty years ago, women were beaten,
قبل ثلاثون عاما , النساء كن يضربن
they were stalked, they were raped,
كن يتربص بهن , و كن يغتصبن
and no one talked about it.
و لم يكن احد يتكلم عن هذا .
There was no justice.
لم تكن هنالك عدالة .
And as an activist, that was not good enough.
و كحقوقية , لم يكن هذا جيد يما فيه الكفاية .
And so step one on this journey
فكانت الخطوة الاولى في هذه الرحلة
is we organized,
بان قمنا بتنظيم
and we created this extraordinary
و تكوين شبكة خفية
underground network of amazing women
مذهلة من النساء الرائعات .
who opened shelters,
الاتي قمن بفتح الملاجئ ,
and if they didn't open a shelter,
و اذا لم يفتحو الملاجئ
they opened their home
قمن بفتح منازلهن
so that women and children could be safe.
لكي يكون النساء و الاطفال في مأمن .
And you know what else we did?
و هل تعرفون ماذا فعلنا ايضا ؟
We had bake sales, we had car washes,
لقد قمنا ببيع المعجنات , و غسلنا السيارا ت ,
and we did everything we could do to fundraise,
و فعلنا كل ما بوسعنا لجمع التبرعات ,
and then at one point we said,
و بعد ذالك في لحظة ما قلنا
you know, it's time that we went
هل تعرفون , انه الوقت الذي يجب ان نذهب
to the federal government
فيه الى الحكومة الفدرالية
and asked them to pay for these
و طلبنا منهم ان يقوموا بتمويل هذه
extraordinary services that are saving people's lives.
الخدمات المذهلة التي تقوم بأنقاذ حياة الناس .
Right? (Applause)
اليس كذلك ؟ (تصفيق )
And so, step number two,
اما الخطوة الثانية ,
we knew we needed to change the laws.
لقد ادركنا بأنه ينبغي ان نغير القوانين .
And so we went to Washington,
و لذلك ذهبنا الى واشنطون ,
and we lobbied for the first piece of legislation.
و قمنا بالضغط من اجل اول جزء من التشريع
And I remember walking through the halls
و اتذكر عندما مشيت عبر ردهة
of the U.S. Capitol,
مبنى ( U.S. Capitol)
and I was in my 30s, and my life had purpose,
و كنت حينها في الثلاثين من عمري , و كان هنالك مغزى من حياتي ,
and I couldn't imagine
و لم أكن أتخيل
that anybody would ever challenge
بأن احد ما سوف يتحدى
this important piece of legislation.
هذا الجزء من التشريع .
I was probably 30 and naive.
كنت حينها بعمر الثلاثين و ساجذة على الارجح
But I heard about a congressman
و لكني سمعت عن عضو في الكونجرس
who had a very, very different point of view.
لديه نظرة مختلفة جدا جدا .
Do you know what he called
هل تعلمون ماذا اطلق
this important piece of legislation?
على هذا التشريع المهم ؟
He called it the Take the Fun Out of Marriage Act.
اطلق عليه ( قانون اخذ المتعة من الزواج ) .
The Take the Fun Out of Marriage Act.
( قانون اخذ المتعة من الزواج )
Ladies and gentlemen, that was in 1984
سيداتي سادتي , هذا كان في عام 1984
in the United States, and I wish I had Twitter.
في الولايات المتحدة , و اتمنى لو كنت امتلك حسابا في ( Twitter )
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Ten years later, after lots of hard work,
بعد مضي عشر سنين , بعد الكثير من العمل المضني ,
we finally passed the Violence Against Women Act,
اخيرا قمنا بتمرير قانون العنف ضد النساء ,
which is a life-changing act
الذي هو قانون مغير للحياة
that has saved so many lives. (Applause)
و الذي قام بانقاذ حياة العديد ( تصفيق )
Thank you.
اشكركم جميعا .
I was proud to be part of that work,
شعرت بالفخر لكوني جزء من ذالك
and it changed the laws
لقد غير ايضا القوانين
and it put millions of dollars into local communities.
و قام بضخ ملاين الدولارات الى المجتمحات المحلية
And you know what else it did? It collected data.
و هل تعرقون ماذا فعل ايضا ؟ لقد جمع البيانات
And I have to tell you, I'm passionate about data.
و اريد ان اخبركم بأني شغوفة بالبيانات
In fact, I am a data nerd.
بالفعل انني مهوسة بالبيانات .
I'm sure there are a lot of data nerds here.
انني متأكدة بوجود الكثير من الشغوفين بالبيانات
I am a data nerd,
انني شغوفة بالبيانات
and the reason for that is I want to make sure
و السبب هو انني اريد ان اتأكد
that if we spend a dollar, that the program works,
باننا اذا انفقنا دولارا سوف تنجح خطتنا
and if it doesn't work, we should change the plan.
و اذا لم تنجح سوف نضطر الى تغير الخطة .
And I also want to say one other thing:
و اريد ايضا ان اقول شي اخر :
We are not going to solve this problem
لن نستطيع حل هذه المشكلة
by building more jails
ببناء سجون اكثر
or by even building more shelters.
او حتى ببناء الملاجئ .
It is about economic empowerment for women,
ان الحل يكمن في تقوية النساء اقتصاديا ,
it is about healing kids who are hurt,
ان الحل يكمن في معالجة الاطفال المتالمين
and it is about prevention with a capital P.
و ان الحل يكمن في الوقاية .
And so, step number three on this journey:
ثم , الخطوة الثالث في هذه الرحلة :
We know, if we're going to keep making this progress,
علمنا بأننا اذا اردنا الاستمرار بهذا التقدم
we're going to have to turn up the volume,
يجب علينا زيادة نشاطاتنا
we're going to have to increase the visibility,
يجب علينا ان نزيد من الوضوح
and we're going to have to engage the public.
و سوف يتوجب علينا ان نشارك الجمهور
And so knowing that, we went to the Advertising Council,
علما بذالك , ذهبنا الى ( Advertising Council )
and we asked them to help us
و طلبنا منهم تقديم المساعدة لنا
build a public education campaign.
من اجل تنظيم حملة تعليمية عامة
And we looked around the world to Canada
فالتفتنا حول العالم , الى كندا
and Australia and Brazil and parts of Africa,
و استراليا و البرازيل و انحاء من افريقيا
and we took this knowledge
و اخذنا تلك المعلومة
and we built the first national
و نظمنا أول حملة
public education campaign
قومية تعليمة عامة
called There's No Excuse for Domestic Violence.
اطلقنا عليها ( لا يوجد عذر للعنف المنزلي )
Take a look at one of our spots.
انظرو الى احد اعلاناتنا .
(Video) Man: Where's dinner?
(فيدو) الرجل : اين العشاء ؟
Woman: Well, I thought you'd be home a couple hours ago, and I put everything away, so—
المرأة : ظننت بأنك ستكون هنا قبل ساعات , و لذلك وضعت كل شي بعيدا , لذالك ...
Man: What is this? Pizza. Woman: If you had just called me, I would have known—
الرجل : ماهذا ؟ بيتزا . المرأة : لو قمت بالاتصال بي , كنت لادرك ...
Man: Dinner? Dinner ready is a pizza? Woman: Honey, please don't be so loud.
الرجل : العشاء الجاهز هو البيتزا ؟ المرأة : عزيزي , ارجوك لا ترفع صوتك .
Please don't—Let go of me!
ارجوك لا ... دعني !
Man: Get in the kitchen! Woman: No! Help!
الرجل : ادخلي الى المطبخ ! المرأة : لا ! ساعدوني !
Man: You want to see what hurts? (Slaps woman)
الرجل : تريدين ان تعرفي ماذا يؤلم ؟ ( صفع المرأة )
That's what hurts! That's what hurts! (Breaking glass)
هذا ما يولم ! هذا ما يولم ( تحطم زجاج )
Woman: Help me!
المرأة: ساعدوني !
["Children have to sit by and watch. What's your excuse?"]
(&amp;quot;يجب ان يجلس الاطفال و يشاهدو . ما هو عذرك ؟&amp;quot; )
Esta Soler: As we were in the process
استا سولير : عندما كنا في
of releasing this campaign,
مرحلة نشر هذه الحملة ,
O.J. Simpson was arrested
لقد تم اعتقال اوجي سيمبسون
for the murder of his wife and her friend.
لقتل زوجته و صديقتها
We learned that he had a long history
ادركنا بأن لدينا تاريخا طويلا من
of domestic violence.
العنف المنزلي
The media became fixated.
أصبحت وسائل الإعلام تركز اهتمامها.
The story of domestic violence
و قصة العنف المنزلي
went from the back page,
انتقلت من الصفحة الاخيرة ,
but actually from the no-page, to the front page.
و لكن حقا من عدم الوجود الى الصفحة الاولى .
Our ads blanketed the airwaves,
اعلاناتنا انتشرت في كل مكان ,
and women, for the first time,
و لاول مرة قمن النساء
started to tell their stories.
بالبدء بسرد قصصهن
Movements are about moments,
نجاح الحملات يتمحور حول اللحظات ,
and we seized this moment.
و نحن استغللنا تلك اللحظة .
And let me just put this in context.
دعوني اضع هذا في سياق الموضوع
Before 1980, do you have any idea
قبل عام 1980 , هل تملكون ادنى فكرة
how many articles were in The New York Times
عن عدد المقالات التي نشرتها صحيفة ( The New York Times )
on domestic violence?
حول العنف المنزلي ؟
I'll tell you: 158.
دعوني اخبركم : 158
And in the 2000s, over 7,000.
و بعد عام 2000 اكثر من 7000 الف مقال .
We were obviously making a difference.
كنا نحدث فارقا بالفعل
But we were still missing a critical element.
و لكنا كنا لا نزلال نفقد عنصرا ضروري
So, step four: We needed to engage men.
ثم , الخطوى الرابعة : كان علينا ان نقوم باشراك الرجال
We couldn't solve this problem
لم نستطيع حل تلك المشكلة
with 50 percent of the population on the sidelines.
مع تهميش 50 في المئة من السكان
And I already told you I'm a data nerd.
و لقد اخبرتكم من قبل بأنني مهوسة بابيانات .
National polling told us that men felt indicted
اخبرتنا الاستطلاعات القومية بأن الرجال شعروا بانهم متهمون
and not invited into this conversation.
و بانه لم يدعوا الى هذه المحادثة .
So we wondered, how can we include men?
لذالك فكرنا , كيف لنا بأن نشرك الرجال
How can we get men to talk about
كيف لنا ان نجعل الرجال يتكلمون عن
violence against women and girls?
العنف ضد النساء و البنات
And a male friend of mine pulled me aside
و صديق ذكر اخذني جانبا
and he said, "You want men to talk about violence
و قال لي &amp;quot; تريدين ان يتكلم الرجال عن العنف
against women and girls. Men don't talk."
ضد النساء و البنات . الرجال لا يتكلمون &amp;quot;
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
I apologize to the men in the audience.
اعتذر الى الرجال الحاضرون
I know you do.
اعلم انكم تتكلمون .
But he said, "Do you know what they do do?
لكن قال , &amp;quot; هل تعلمين ماذا يفعلون ؟
They do talk to their kids.
يتكلمون مع اطفالهم .
They talk to their kids as parents, as coaches."
يتكلمون مع اطفالهم كأبائهم , كمدربيهم .&amp;quot;
And that's what we did.
وكان ذالك ما فعلناه .
We met men where they were at
قابلنا الرجال حيث كانو
and we built a program.
و قمنا ببناء برنامج .
And then we had this one event
و من ثم كان هنالك حدث
that stays in my heart forever
سوف يظل في قلبي الى الابد
where a basketball coach
حيث كان مدرب كرة السلة
was talking to a room filled with male athletes
يتكلم في غرفة مليئة بالرياضين الذكور
and men from all walks of life.
و رجال من جميع مناحي الحياة .
And he was talking about the importance
و كان يتكلم عن اهمية
of coaching boys into men
تدريب الاولاد ليكي يصبحو رجالا
and changing the culture of the locker room
و تغير ثقافة غرفة تغير الملابس
and giving men the tools to have healthy relationships.
و اعطاء الرجال الادوات للحصول على علاقات صحية .
And all of a sudden, he looked at the back of the room,
و فجاة نظر الى اخر الغرفة ,
and he saw his daughter,
و رأى ابنته
and he called out his daughter's name, Michaela,
و قام بمناداة اسم ابنته &amp;quot; ميكايلا&amp;quot;
and he said, "Michaela, come up here."
و قال &amp;quot; ميكايلا &amp;quot; تعالي هنا &amp;quot;
And she's nine years old, and she was kind of shy,
كانت في التاسعة من عمرها و كانت خجولة
and she got up there,
و ذهبت الى هناك ,
and he said, "Sit down next to me."
و قال لها, &amp;quot; اجلسي بجانبي &amp;quot;.
She sat right down next to him.
جلست بجانبه .
He gave her this big hug, and he said,
قام بمعانفتها بشدة و قال ,
"People ask me why I do this work.
&amp;quot; يسألني الناس لماذا اقوم بهذا العمل .
I do this work because I'm her dad,
اقوم بهذا لانني والدها ,
and I don't want anyone ever to hurt her."
و لا اريد لاي شخص بأن يوذيها &amp;quot;
And as a parent, I get it.
و كأب , افهم ذالك
I get it,
افهم
knowing that there are so many sexual assaults
ادراكا منا بأن هناك الكثير من الاعتدائات الجنسية
on college campuses
في حرم الجامعة
that are so widespread and so under-reported.
حيث انها منتشرة على نطاق واسع لا كنه قليلا ما يبلغ عنها
We've done a lot for adult women.
فعلنا الكثير من اجل النساء الراشدات.
We've got to do a better job for our kids.
يجب علينا ان نقوم بعمل افضل من اجل ابنائنا .
We just do. We have to. (Applause)
يجب علينا القيام بهذا . ( تصفيق )
We've come a long way
لقد احرزنا الكثير من التقدم
since the days of the Polaroid.
منذ ايام ( كاميرا ) البولارويد .
Technology has been our friend.
التكنلوجيا كانت صديقتنا .
The mobile phone is a global game changer
الهاتف النقال مغير عالمي
for the empowerment of women,
لتقوية النساء ,
and Facebook and Twitter and Google and YouTube
و فيسبوك و تويتر و غوغول و يوتوب
and all the social media helps us organize
و جميغ شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي ساعدت في تنظيمنا
and tell our story in a powerful way.
و سرد قصصنا بطريقة اكثر تاثيرا
And so those of you in this audience
و الى من في الحضور
who have helped build those applications
من ساعدتم في بناء التطبيقات
and those platforms, as an organizer,
و تلك المنابر , كمنظمة
I say, thank you very much.
اشكركم جميعا
Really. I clap for you.
حقا . اصفق لكم
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
I'm the daughter of a man
انني ابنة رجل
who joined one club in his life,
انضم الى ناد واحد في حياته ,
the Optimist Club.
نادي المتفائلون
You can't make that one up.
لا يمكنك اختلاق ذالك .
And it is his spirit and his optimism
و ان روحة و تفاؤله
that is in my DNA.
في حمضي النووي
I have been doing this work
لازلت افعل هذا
for over 30 years,
لمدة اكثر من ثلاثون عاما
and I am convinced, now more than ever,
و انني مقتنعة , الان اكثر من السابق
in the capacity of human beings to change.
في مقدرة البشر في التغيير
I believe we can bend the arc of human history
اؤمن بأننا يمكن ان نغير تاريخ البشرية
toward compassion and equality,
نحو التعاطف و المساواة
and I also fundamentally believe
و ايضا اؤمن
and passionately believe
و اؤمن بشغف
that this violence does not have to be part
بان هذا العنف لا يجب ان يكون جزأ
of the human condition.
من حالة الانسان
And I ask you, stand with us
و اسالكم , ان تقفو الى جانبنا
as we create futures without violence
من أجل بناء مستقبل بدون عنف
for women and girls and men and boys everywhere.
من اجل النساء و البنات و الرجال و الاولاد في كل مكان
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا .
(Applause)
( تصفيق )